{
  "waves":
  [
    {"question":"Define frequency and give its units.", "answer": "The number of waves passing through a point per second. (hertz) Hz"},
    {"question":"Define wavelength.", "answer": "The distance between two adjacent peaks on a wave."},
    {"question":"Define amplitude.", "answer": "The maximum displacement of the wave from its equilibrium position."},
    {"question":"How can you find out the time period of a wave using it frequency?", "answer": "T = 1/F"},
    {"question":"What is phase difference and what is it measured in?", "answer": "How much a particle / wave lags behind another particle / wave. Measured in radians, degrees or fractions of a cycle."},
    {"question":"What is a longitudinal wave?", "answer": "A wave in which the oscillation of the particles is parallel to the direction of energy transfer. There are rarefactions (areas of low pressure) and compressions (areas of high pressure)."},
    {"question":"What is a transverse wave? Give examples. ", "answer": "Waves where the particle oscillations are perpendicular to the direction of energy transfer."},
    {"question":" How fast do electromagnetic waves travel in a vacuum?", "answer": "3 x 10^8 m/s"},
    {"question":"True or False? The magnetic field and electric field in a electromagnetic wave are parallel to each other.", "answer": "False. The electric and magnetic field are at right angles to each other. "},
    {"question":"What does a polarising filter do?", "answer": "Only allows oscillations in one plane."},
    {"question":"How is polarisation used as evidence of the nature of transverse waves?", "answer": "Polarisation can only occur if a wave’s oscillations are perpendicular to its direction of travel (as they are in transverse waves)."},
    {"question":"How is polarisation used in antennas?", "answer": "TV and radio signals are usually plane-polarised by the orientation of the rods on the transmitting aerial, so the receiving aerial must be aligned in the same plane of polarisation to receive the signal at full strength."},
    {"question":"What is a stationary wave?", "answer": "A wave which transfers no energy and whose positions of maximum and minimum amplitude are constant."},
    {"question":"What is a node?", "answer": "A point on a stationary wave where the displacement is 0."},
    {"question":"What is an antinode?", "answer": "A point on a stationary wave with maximum displacement."},
    {"question":"What are the conditions for a stationary wave to be produced?", "answer": "The waves must be of the same frequency, wavelength and amplitude.   /  They must be travelling in opposite directions"},
    {"question":"Describe the first harmonic for a stationary wave with two closed ends. ", "answer": "t consists of 2 nodes at either end and an antinode in the middle."}
  ],
  "mechanics":
  [
    {"question":"What is meant by a scalar quantity?", "answer": "A quantity that has only magnitude."},
    {"question":"What is a vector quantity?", "answer": "A quantity that has magnitude as well as direction."},
    {"question":"Is acceleration a vector or scalar quantity?", "answer": "Vector."},
    {"question":"Is mass a scalar or vector quantity?", "answer": "Scalar."},
    {"question":"What is the difference between mass and weight?", "answer": "Mass is scalar and is not dependent on the gravity acting upon it. Weight is a vector and depends on the gravitational field strength. / W = mg"},
    {"question":"If an object is in equilibrium the sum of the anti clockwise moments would be", "answer": "Equal to the sum of the clockwise moments (principle of moments)."},
    {"question":"How can the forces acting on a object be shown to be in equilibrium?", "answer": "Adding the horizontal and vertical components of the forces acting on it, showing they equal zero. / Or if there are 3 forces acting on the object youcan draw a scale diagram, if the scale diagram forms a closed triangle, then the object is in equilibrium."},
    {"question":"What is a moment?", "answer": "A turning force: force multiplied by the perpendicular distance from the point to the line of action of the force."},
    {"question":"What is meant by a couple?", "answer": "A pair of equal and opposite coplanar forces."},
    {"question":"What is meant by the centre of mass?", "answer": "The point through which all the mass of an object acts, for a uniform object the centre of mass is the centre of the object"}
  ],
  "materials":
  [
    {"question":"What is Hooke’s law?", "answer": "Extension (∆L) is directly proportional to force applied (F), given that the environmental conditions are kept constant."},
    {"question":"What equation is used to calculate density?", "answer": "Density = Mass / Volume"},
    {"question":"What is meant by tensile stress?", "answer": "The force applied per unit cross sectional area."},
    {"question":"What is tensile strain?", "answer": "A measure of how the material stretches: the extension (ΔL) divided by the original length (L), strain has no units."},
    {"question":"What is the difference between elastic and plastic deformation?", "answer": "Elastic deformation: when the force is removed the object will return to its original shape. / Plastic deformation: after the load is removed the object will not return to its original shape."},
    {"question":"What is breaking stress?", "answer": "The minimum stress needed to break a material."},
    {"question":"What is meant when a material is described as brittle?", "answer": "It doesn’t deform plastically but breaks when the stress reaches a certain value."},
    {"question":"What is the elastic limit?", "answer": "The force above which the material will be plastically deformed (permanently stretched)."},
    {"question":"How do you find the Young’s modulus from a stress-strain graph?", "answer": "The gradient of the line."},
    {"question":"How can a force-extension graph show Hooke’s Law is being obeyed?", "answer": "When it is a straight line through the origin ie. force and extension are directly proportional."}
  ]
},
{
  "waves_Wanswers":
  [
    {"Answer1":"A position of maximum displacement in a stationary wave. ", "Answer2": " The spreading of waves as they pass through a gap of a similar magnitude to their wavelength", "Answer 3":"A position of minimum displacement in a stationary wave"},  
    {"Answer1":"A material property that is equal to the ratio between the speed of light in a vacuum, and the speed of light in a given material.", "Answer2": "A law linking a wave’s angle of incidence to its angle of refraction, with the use of the refractive indexes of the mediums involved.", "Answer 3":" The product of a wave’s frequency and wavelength"},
    {"Answer1":"A wave with oscillations that are perpendicular to the direction of energy propagation. Electromagnetic waves are examples of transverse waves", "Answer2": "The restriction of a wave so that it can only oscillate in a single plane. This can only occur for transverse waves", "Answer 3":"TV and radio signals are usually plane-polarised by the orientation of the rods on the transmitting aerial, so the receiving aerial must be aligned in the same plane of polarisation to receive the signal at full strength."},
    {"Answer1":"Waves are coherent if they have the same wavelength and frequency, as well as there being a fixed phase difference between them. ", "Answer2": "The number of waves that pass a point in a unit time period. It is the inverse of the time period", "Answer 3":"The distance between two adjacent bright fringes or two adjacent dark fringes"},
    {"Answer1":"A light source that produces a collimated and coherent beam", "Answer2": "The name given to the superposition of waves that occurs when two waves meet. If the waves are in phase they will constructively interfere, but if they are out of phase, they will destructively interfere.", "Answer 3":""},
    {"Answer1":" A protective layer on an optical fibre to improve the tensile strength of the fibre, prevent scratching and to prevent signal transfer between adjacent fibres. ", "Answer2": "A wave that stores, but does not transfer, energy", "Answer 3":" A material property that is equal to the ratio between the speed of light in a vacuum, and the speed of light in a given material."},
    {"Answer1":"A wave’s maximum displacement from its equilibrium position.", "Answer2": " A position of maximum displacement in a stationary wave. ", "Answer 3":""},
    {"Answer1":"Filter that blocks all light", "Answer2": "filter that blocks no light", "Answer 3":"nothing"},
    {"Answer1":"it is not used in antennas", "Answer2": "TV and radio signals longitudinal waves so not possible", "Answer 3":"transmits energy"},
    {"Answer1":"Occurs only when the particle oscillations are perpindicular to wave propogation", "Answer2": "Transfers energy energy through the filter which proves that it is transverse", "Answer 3":"Transfers no energy therefore proving that it is transverse"}
    
  ],
  "Mechanics_WAnswers":
  [
       {"Answer1":"The maximum stress that an object can withstand before failure occurs.", "Answer2": " A brittle object will show very little strain before reaching its breaking stress. ", "Answer 3":"The single point through which all the mass of an object can be said to act"},  
    {"Answer1":"Two equal and opposite parallel forces that act on an object through different lines of action. It has the effect of causing a rotation without translation", "Answer2": " The mass per unit volume of a material.", "Answer 3":"The ratio of useful output to total input for a given system"},
    {"Answer1":"neither", "Answer2": "Vector", "Answer 3":"Both"},
    {"Answer1":"Mass and weight are the same", "Answer2": "mass is a vector and weight is a scaler", "Answer 3":"They both represent the same thing just with a different name"},
    {"Answer1":"the sum of the anti clockwise moments would be", "Answer2": "The sum of no moments ", "Answer 3":" The sum of Kinetic Energies"},
    {"Answer1":"By taking away the forces from each other", "Answer2": "By multiplying the components together to show how large the value will be ", "Answer 3":"Diving the components together"},
    {"Answer1":"The mass per unit volume of a material", "Answer2": "Two equal and opposite parallel forces that act on an object through different lines of action. It has the effect of causing a rotation without translation.", "Answer 3":"The ratio of useful output to total input for a given system"},
    {"Answer1":"The product of an object’s mass and velocity", "Answer2": "A non Turning Force", "Answer 3":"A scalar unit"},
    {"Answer1":"A pair of equal and opposite forces ", "Answer2": "A point that is not on the object", "Answer 3":"A Quantum figure that relates to the mass of an object"}
  ], 
    "Materials_WAnswers":
  [
       {"Answer1":"Extension (∆L) is NOT directly proportional to force applied (F), given that the environmental conditions are kept constant.", "Answer2": "Force is Inverserly proportional to the energy gained by the spring ", "Answer 3":"A collision in which the total kinetic energy of the system before the collision is not equal to the kinetic energy of the system after the collision"},  
    {"Answer1":"volume/mass", "Answer2": "surface area/ Weight", "Answer 3":"Force * perpindicular distance from the line of action"},
    {"Answer1":"The force divided by the cross-sectional area ", "Answer2": "A relative figure that has no unit relating to moments ", "Answer 3":"strain is the definition of how a material works"},
    {"Answer1":"Elastic deformation is when the object will not return to its original shape whilst plastic deformation does return to its original shape", "Answer2": "Elastic deformation is the force applied to an object and is held constant whilst plastic is a temporary force applied", "Answer 3":"Elastic deformation is the equation - P=IV -"},
    {"Answer1":"The maximum stress needed to break a material", "Answer2": "The maximum value that a point will return to its original shape", "Answer 3":"The minimum value required to permanently deform an object "},
    {"Answer1":"A measure of how difficult it is to stretch a given object.", "Answer2": "A scalar quantity is one that only has a magnitude. Examples include length, mass and temperature", "Answer 3":"The ratio of stress to strain for a given material. Its unit is the Pascal (Pa)"},
    {"Answer1":"The single point through which all the mass of an object can be said to act", "Answer2": "mass per unit volume of a material", "Answer 3":" A collision in which the total kinetic energy of the system before the collision is equal to the total kinetic energy of the system after the collision"},
    {"Answer1":"The extension of an elastic object will be directly proportional to the force applied to it up to the object’s limit of proportionality", "Answer2": "The product of a force and the perpendicular distance from the line of action of the force to the pivot", "Answer 3":"The maximum speed of an object that occurs when the resistive and driving forces acting on the object are equal to each other"},
    {"Answer1":"extension of an elastic object will be directly proportional to the force applied to it up to the object’s limit of proportionality", "Answer2": " A vector quantity is one that has both a magnitude and a direction. Examples include velocity, displacement and acceleration", "Answer 3":"The maximum speed of an object that occurs when the resistive and driving forces acting on the object are equal to each other"},
    {"Answer1":"When it is curved line not passing through the origin ", "Answer2": "A straight line that does not pass through the origin", "Answer 3":"When there is no correlation between the data points being applied."}
  ] 
  
  
}
